<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://signebedi.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://signebedi.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-03-17T20:08:02+00:00</updated><id>https://signebedi.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Software Engineer. Classicist. Social Scientist. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">how i take notes</title><link href="https://signebedi.github.io/blog/2025/how-i-take-notes/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="how i take notes"/><published>2025-03-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://signebedi.github.io/blog/2025/how-i-take-notes</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://signebedi.github.io/blog/2025/how-i-take-notes/"><![CDATA[<p>As a part of the course I currently teach at the University of Wisconsin called Legal Studies 444: Law in Action, I developed a lesson plan on “taking effective notes for law school (and life)” and have taken to giving this lecture to students early in the semester so that they can (hopefully) apply some of its takeaways as the course develops. Beforehand, I ask them to prepare two readings: first, an essay from GULC emeritus professor Robin West on the path to becoming law faculty; second, the introduction to <em>How to Take Smart Notes</em> by Sönke Ahrens. The point is to encourage them to conceptualize their legal education as both a practical and theoretical endeavor, and their notes as serving both a present and future purpose. I’m including the substance of this lecture in the essay below, and follow this up with a deep-dive into how you can organize your notes using the story of a hypothetical second-year law student, Jade Law.</p> <h4 id="i-law-as-knowledge-management">I. Law as Knowledge Management</h4> <p>If most of what you know about law school comes from television, then you’ll be forgiven for believing that law school is mostly about producing legal practitioners. There’s lots of reasons why this may be the case: legal practice comes with wealth, prestige, and a direct impact on the lives of your clients and society writ large. However, legal practitioners also are simultaneously legal thinkers, especially those who are in roles where they need to conduct research to properly advise their clients. Further, plenty of practicing lawyers engage in outside research and publish this research in their free time, too. Likewise, appellate judges, clerks, and attorneys are all engaging in legal thinking to establish legitimate legal standards, argue their cases, and make sense of the law. So, it’s not clear that legal practitioners constitute a distinct category from legal thinkers.</p> <p>Given that there’s so much thinking involved in legal practice, we might ask whether law school primarily about producing practicing lawyers or producing legal thinkers. Robin West’s essay is striking in its claim that, to become a competitive candidate for a position as a law professor - which I am employing here as a proxy for the typical legal thinker, one need only write a law review article and take some interdisciplinary classes. Other than that, you’re free to take other classes as usual in law school. Does that make it sound like law schools are primarily focused on legal practice? Of course, there is also a secondary issue of academic performance - law faculty postings are hotly contested. Likewise, the student experience will vary from law school to law school, as some institutions and their faculty might have a greater focus on practical rather than theoretical pursuits. But what West’s essay suggests is that law school is more than a little bit oriented toward legal thought, not just legal practice.<d-footnote>Though this is sometimes a point of critique, see eg. Sullivan et al. (2007); notably, the University of Wisconsin has sought to address this through its Law in Action curriculum</d-footnote> I would suggest that we should understand legal thinking as inextricably linked with an individual’s ability to manage knowledge.</p> <p>I should briefly note how my own thinking on this subject has developed over time. As a second-year law student at the University of Wisconsin, I took a course on state and local government with Professor Miriam Seifter. Beyond helping me grasp key concepts, Professor Seifter introduced me to a robust literature on legal culture. In particular, she shared the work of Steven Teles and Amanda Hollis-Brusky on conservative legal networks in the United States, as well as her own scholarship on constitutional communities.<d-footnote>See Telles (2010), Hollis-Brusky (2019), Seifter (2022)</d-footnote> These ideas tie into my broader interest in what we might refer to as epistemic communities—groups that shape, produce, and sustain knowledge—and intersect with related scholarly discussions on elites, caste, and the institutional transmission of expertise. Later in the semester teaching Legal Studies 444, I build upon our discussion of knowledge and expertise to explore how legal culture shapes and structures specific areas of the law. I remain convinced that personal methods for managing knowledge and expertise are closely linked to the social practice of law and to the development of discourses and intellectual traditions on topics of great consequence to the legal community.</p> <h4 id="ii-competing-goals-and-the-slip-box-method">II. Competing Goals and the Slip Box Method</h4> <p>If we accept that the structure of law school is naturally oriented toward legal thought, then we should ask ourselves whether our personal knowledge management systems or note-taking methodologies are sufficient in order to lead us to success in that arena. We need no detailed excursus to understand the range of different ways that people take notes. Many take notes by hand, a few dictate their notes, and some take no notes at all. There are a variety of applications available for digital note taking, like Microsoft Word or OneNote, Google Drive, Evernote, Notion, Confluence, Vim, Emacs, and Notepad - to name only a few. Beyond platforms for note taking, different methods are available to us to organize our notes: we can use a directory hierarchy to keep our notes separate, organize notes by date, or use tags as ways of cross linking notes with overlapping subject matter. The most important takeaway I emphasize to my students is that they have a system that works for them. Indeed, when it comes to taking effective notes, ‘to thine own self be true.’</p> <p>Sönke Ahrens’ book is helpful in understanding how we can be true to ourselves while also developing a system that is effective. We need to start by asking what our goal is in taking notes. Ahrens distinguishes between planners and experts, where a planner is trying to anticipate demands and orient their knowledge management system to complete those demands. For example, you might plan around completing assignments for a class and getting an A. An expert, on the other hand, is concerned primarily with learning things and becoming masters of their craft. A ‘planning’ goal could be relevant to a student that wants to organize their notes to maximize short-run outcomes, while an ‘expertise’ goal could be relevant to one who wants to organize their notes to maximize long-run outcomes. While I would argue that we should understand these goals as competing with one another, to be sure, and my personal preference is for the ‘expertise’ goal, I understand that students are going to be anxious about their grades. My claim is that you can develop a note taking system that accounts for both goals simultaneously, and that good grades in law school often come down to your effectiveness as an ‘expert’ and not a ‘planner.’</p> <p>Some of my students shared note taking methods that they use that allow them to interlink ideas and sort them into their short run and long run usefulness. The problem with some of these approaches is generally that they increase in complexity as time progresses and they take lots of time to maintain. Wouldn’t it be nice to have a method that remains simple and scalable over time? This is where the slip-note method, so some variation therein, comes into play. This is a method where you stack new notes on top of each other, and connect them as you go. I like to think of this as ‘knowledge management on the go’. It’s a complex system, to be sure, but not in a way that necessarily grows unmanageable. Rather, it’s conceptually complex and enables increasing complexity of thought, especially when you take notes that span multiple disciplines. It’s not something that you need to get perfect the moment you start it. In fact, those that use it tend to discourage that attitude of perfectionism which can make note taking a very unenjoyable and laborious process.<d-footnote>See eg. Vik (2020)</d-footnote></p> <h4 id="iii-taking-notes-with-obsidian">III. Taking Notes with Obsidian</h4> <p>There are a handful of tools that facilitate the structure I’ve shared above. While many applications will do, my experience is that tools that enable you to tag or link notes with each other are best suited to this method. My preferred app is <a href="https://obsidian.md/download">Obsidian</a> (yes, I am one of those cultists) because it makes it easy to write notes and use tagging systems to link these notes together as you progress, allowing its users to take notes to serve a simultaneous present day purpose and long run purpose without needing to spend substantial time and energy sorting these notes, and without significantly increasing the complexity of managing these notes and organizing them together as time progresses. It’s also open source, with a <a href="https://forum.obsidian.md">substantial community</a>, a grand number of <a href="https://obsidian.md/plugins">plugins</a>, and several helpful commentators.<d-footnote>My favorite commentator is <a href="https://www.youtube.com/c/nicolevanderhoeven">Nicole van der Hoeven</a></d-footnote> It’s important to note that Obsidian uses <a href="https://publish-01.obsidian.md/access/09cfa50ec31c0f01873549787f02a7e0/assets/Markdown%20Cheat%20Sheet.pdf">Markdown</a> formatting. I encourage (but don’t require) my students to try it out, especially if they are considering law school and becoming legal practitioners, given that even practitioners have to work with knowledge, and it’s especially true for those who want to go to law school and become legal scholars, because the vast majority of their work will be involved with knowledge management and expertise around a subject matter.</p> <p>Take my case as an example to inform your decision making on this issue. I am an interdisciplinary fellow with interests and expertise that span the arts and humanities, law and the social sciences, and computer science. As such, the note taking system that I’ve built does its best to (at least) accommodate these and (at best) allow them each to contribute to growth in the global complexity of thought I’m able to achieve. I also maintain a lively correspondence with a wide range of people who also try to address a similar set of knowledge management problems - at least, atmospherically similar, though the particular textures of their interests and goals may vary from each other and also from mine. Variety, however, is the spice of life, and I think that talking about my system with other people with different attitudes towards notes and different particular interests has allowed me to understand myself better and refine my system to better conform to my needs. This is probably what Tiago Forte means by ‘building a second brain.’ <d-footnote>Forte (2022)</d-footnote></p> <p>If you’ve read this far, I will assume you are open to trying out Obsidian. If so, I’ve included a few subsections below for you to consider when developing your personal knowledge management system. To illustrate how these ideas play out in practice, let’s consider Jade Law, a second-year law student looking to revamp her note-taking approach.</p> <h4 id="a-tags-links-and-a-dusting-of-organization">a. tags, links, and a dusting of organization</h4> <p>Jade is tired of using Google Drive to organize her notes. In the past, she would create a separate folder for each of her classes, and store her notes in a single, very large Google Doc outline, with readings and slides stored separately in the same folder. When exam time rolls around, she struggles to cross-reference her notes against each individual set of slides, and after the semester is done, the large Google Doc outline is hard to search and sits obliquely, ignored forever more. Within her outline, she would create headers by class date, and then she’d create a topical outline at the top of the document around exam time to re-arrange information best suited to prepare her for her final assessment.</p> <p>Tired of this approach, she downloads Obsidian and creates a set of folders to cover cases, concepts, people, meetings, and class notes, see the image below. This is what I refer to as a ‘dusting of organization’ - a terminology I’m adapting from a particularly apt blog post by Joel Spolsky.<d-footnote>Spolsky (2018)</d-footnote> What I mean by this is that, as a human with limited capacity to make sense of visual information before I become distracted and overwhelmed, I prefer using a slight-but-unobtrusive set of folders to create organizational barriers to information, such that I can understand the list of files that I’m staring at in any given situation. This directory hierarchy need not, and probably should not, recurse too deeply, since that works against the easy availability of information. But, it can if that’s how you like it.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/2025-03-12-obs_left_nav-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/2025-03-12-obs_left_nav-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/2025-03-12-obs_left_nav-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/2025-03-12-obs_left_nav.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> The left navigation panel in Obsidian, showing file structure using the File Tree Alternative plugin described in a subsequent section (source: author) </div> <p>Just as soon as Jade has created this set of folders into which to sort her relevant notes and documents, she begins to break those barriers down by employing a set of tags and links to other files, so that the interlinks between different ideas can begin to manifest. For example, she begins writing a note on the Supreme Court case Brady v. Maryland for her criminal law course. In it, she adds a tag for the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">#brady-rule</code> so that she can reference this idea in future notes. She also links the document to a separate note she’s previously written on the Warren Court, since she’d like to keep track of the cases she reads that were decided during that period. She adds this to the ‘frontmatter’ of the note by typing <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">---</code> on the first line of her note on Brady v. Maryland, which opens an interface like the one you can see in the image below. She then adds a link by typing <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">[[Warren Court]]</code> into the field she’s created for this value, which creates a bi-directional link between two notes. This is another way in which this system allows her thinking to grow in complexity without necessarily increasing the complexity of managing the system itself.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/2025-03-12-obs_example_note-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/2025-03-12-obs_example_note-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/2025-03-12-obs_example_note-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/2025-03-12-obs_example_note.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> An example Obsidian note describing a legal case (source: author) </div> <p>Jade likes the idea of being able to read class slides and readings directly alongside the notes that she takes. To do this, she starts embedding these directly into the notes that she takes, as in the image below.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/2025-03-12-obs_pdf_embedding-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/2025-03-12-obs_pdf_embedding-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/2025-03-12-obs_pdf_embedding-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/2025-03-12-obs_pdf_embedding.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Embedding a PDF within an Obsidian note for reference and annotation (source: author) </div> <p>Around exam time, Jade can use an efficient keyword search for topics to track down more information from class - or other classes where she’s read similar cases. She can also use Graph View to plot out the interlinked ideas and tags from the various classes she has taken, as in the image below. This constellation view can be useful, or not - but there are other plugins like Dataview (referenced in a subsequent section) or Excalibrain that can extend this functionality significantly to assist with mind mapping around exam time.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/2025-03-12-obs_graph_view-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/2025-03-12-obs_graph_view-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/2025-03-12-obs_graph_view-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/2025-03-12-obs_graph_view.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> The graph view in Obsidian visualizing connections between notes and tags (source: author) </div> <p>Jade will sometimes come up with a novel idea that she wants to follow up on later. When this happens, she’ll embed the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">#idea</code> tag next to the idea, so that she can query for all her ideas later on, in case she wants to write more about it. I’ve included an example of this in the image below.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/2025-03-12-obs_idea_tag-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/2025-03-12-obs_idea_tag-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/2025-03-12-obs_idea_tag-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/2025-03-12-obs_idea_tag.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Demonstrating the use of an 'idea' tag in Obsidian (source: author) </div> <h4 id="b-plugins-plugins-plugins">b. plugins, plugins, plugins</h4> <p>I generally recommend four basic plugins for Obsidian, which I’ve described at a high level below.</p> <ol> <li>Excalidraw. This is perhaps one of my favorite tools for building visualizations, charts, and drawings - which is saying a lot, as I’ve spent years using commercial options like Lucidchart and open source alternatives like Draw.io.</li> <li>File Tree Alternative. This is a better view of the folder structure that allows you to exclude certain folders from view, and also change how they are represented on the screen, see the first image above to get a sense of what this plugin looks like.</li> <li>Dataview. This is a system that allows you to run SQL-like queries against notes and their metadata, allowing you to generate eg. dynamic lists of notes that use a particular tag, meetings with a particular person, or notes written within a certain date range.</li> <li>Omnisearch. This is a much more powerful alternative to the default search feature, and allows you to get more out of your searches generally. Sometimes, when you use Obsidian with Git (more on this in a subsequent section), this plugin can force a file database reindex when the application starts up, which can take a few additional seconds.</li> </ol> <p>The broader point, however, is that there is a whole universe of plugins that you’re able to choose from to extend the base functionality of Obsidian. One of the benefits of the system being open source is that the ecosystem is easy to extend. My claim here is that a notetaking application that cannot be easily extended is not really useful, because everyone has a different set of overarching concerns, aesthetic preferences, and configuration needs that necessitate customization. The Obsidian forum and commentators like Nicole van der Hoeven, both referenced earlier in this essay, are great resources for discovering new plugins. For the purpose of the hypothetical, we’ll say that Jade installs the four plugins listed above.</p> <h4 id="c-when-to-use-dates-in-your-note-titles">c. when to use dates in your note titles</h4> <p>I like to use dates in the title of some notes that I take that are ephemeral in nature - like a note from a particular day of class, or a specific meeting - because it makes it easy to keep the notes properly sorted by date when using alphanumeric sorting for a given folder view. It also makes it easier for me to navigate back to a given event using external temporal tools, like a calendar. That said, there are also permanent, conceptual notes that might be linked to multiple ephemeral notes, and which therefore warrants a name which does not contain a date but instead reflects the given topic. In Jade’s case, she chooses to prepend all her class and meeting notes with a date in the format of <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">YYYY-MM-DD</code>, but to have her case, people, and concept notes just follow the name of the subject of the note.</p> <p>This distinction eventually grows more important when you have multiple notes referencing the same set of ideas, court cases, work products, or people. Eventually, you’ll want to develop a central collection point where you can dynamically list the content of the notes that meet some criteria. For example, let’s say Jade has a weekly meeting with a supervising professor as part of a research project she is completing for course credit. She might have a series of meetings where they discuss the topic of the research, and the work product she is completing to satisfy requirements to earn credit. She could choose to write these notes as ephemeral meeting notes, using a naming convention like “YYYY-MM-DD Professor Name” to name these files. She can then use tags, linked references, and tools like the Dataview plugin listed above to create permanent notes that consolidate all these ephemeral notes into a permanent location, ensuring a single point of reference and reducing confusion.</p> <h4 id="d-automate-the-boring-stuff">d. automate the boring stuff</h4> <details><summary>A brief note about the following section</summary> <p>The following section includes advanced techniques and presumes the reader’s familiarity with basic programming principles and tools like the Python programming language and Git. Continue at your own peril.</p> </details> <p>Like Al Sweigart’s <em>Automate the Boring Stuff with Python</em>, the goal of this section is to provide some conventions and throwaway code snippets to help you automate some of the note management steps that, if done manually, take up precious time and mental resources. For example, it’s useful to generate groups of notes ahead of time when possible. For example, if you receive a course syllabus that lists the topics and readings for each day of class, then you can use that to generate a list of notes before the course even begins. This also reduces administrative complexity as the semester progresses by allowing you to create a structure of notes beforehand that you can fill in as you go. Let’s say you want to implement this using python. You can start by creating a dictionary of course dates, as in the snippet below. I typically use the class dates as keys for this dictionary, though you’re free to restructure this however you choose.</p> <div class="language-python highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="kn">import</span> <span class="n">datetime</span>
<span class="kn">import</span> <span class="n">os</span>

<span class="c1"># Here we define the class days and assignment
</span><span class="n">class_days</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">1/23/24</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="p">{</span>
        <span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">description</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">Constitutional challenges to eligibility restrictions</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">,</span>
        <span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">reading</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">Read CB 98-104, 106-14 (through ¶ 3), 116-18 (¶ 6 only)</span><span class="sh">"</span>
    <span class="p">},</span>
    <span class="bp">...</span>
<span class="p">}</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p>Next, we will want to define a function to create a markdown file. We plan to pass it a handful of params, like the date string for a given class session, the contents of the dictionary we defined above, and then (optionally) links to the next and previous class, which we will use to create easy visual tools for cycling through class notes sequentially.</p> <div class="language-python highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="c1"># Here we define a function to create the markdown file
</span><span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">create_markdown_file</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">date_str</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">content</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">previous_class</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="bp">None</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">next_class</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="bp">None</span><span class="p">):</span>
    <span class="c1"># This parses the date string and creates a datetime object
</span>    <span class="n">date</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">datetime</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">datetime</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">strptime</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">date_str</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">%Y-%m-%d</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">)</span>
    
    <span class="c1"># This formats the datetime object from above into a string to use in the filename
</span>    <span class="n">filename</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">date</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">strftime</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sa">f</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">%Y-%m-%d Election Law.md</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">)</span>
    
    <span class="c1"># This portion handles the frontmatter for the markdown file we’re creating
</span>    <span class="n">markdown_header</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="sa">f</span><span class="sh">"""</span><span class="s">---
title: </span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="si">{</span><span class="n">content</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">topic</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">]</span><span class="si">}</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">
previous_class: </span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="si">{</span><span class="sa">f</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">[[</span><span class="si">{</span><span class="n">previous_class</span><span class="si">}</span> <span class="n">Election</span> <span class="n">Law</span><span class="p">]]</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s"> if previous_class else </span><span class="sh">''</span><span class="si">}</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">
next_class: </span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="si">{</span><span class="sa">f</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">[[</span><span class="si">{</span><span class="n">next_class</span><span class="si">}</span> <span class="n">Election</span> <span class="n">Law</span><span class="p">]]</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s"> if next_class else </span><span class="sh">''</span><span class="si">}</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">
tags:
  - election-law
---
</span><span class="sh">"""</span>
    <span class="c1"># Here we construct the body of the markdown file, which just contains the description and the assignment 
</span>    <span class="n">markdown_body</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="sa">f</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="se">\n</span><span class="s"># </span><span class="si">{</span><span class="n">content</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">description</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">]</span><span class="si">}</span><span class="se">\n\n</span><span class="s">**Assignment:**</span><span class="se">\n\n</span><span class="si">{</span><span class="n">content</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">reading</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">]</span><span class="si">}</span><span class="se">\n\n</span><span class="sh">"</span>
    
    <span class="c1"># Finally, we write the frontmatter and body to the markdown file
</span>    <span class="k">with</span> <span class="nf">open</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">filename</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="sh">'</span><span class="s">w</span><span class="sh">'</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="k">as</span> <span class="nb">file</span><span class="p">:</span>
        <span class="nb">file</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">write</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">markdown_header</span><span class="p">)</span>
        <span class="nb">file</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">write</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">markdown_body</span><span class="p">)</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p>To implement this function for each class identified in the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">class_days</code> dictionary above, we can run the following logic:</p> <div class="language-python highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="c1"># We sort the dates sequentially
</span><span class="n">previous_class</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="bp">None</span>
<span class="n">sorted_dates</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nf">sorted</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">class_days</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">keys</span><span class="p">())</span>

<span class="c1"># Then we iterate through each item in the now-sorted dictionary
</span><span class="k">for</span> <span class="n">i</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">date_str</span> <span class="ow">in</span> <span class="nf">enumerate</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">sorted_dates</span><span class="p">):</span>
    <span class="c1"># This is the content of a given day
</span>    <span class="n">content</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">class_days</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="n">date_str</span><span class="p">]</span> 
    
    <span class="c1"># Here we define the next class date if there is one
</span>    <span class="n">next_class</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">sorted_dates</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="n">i</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="k">if</span> <span class="n">i</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="mi">1</span> <span class="o">&lt;</span> <span class="nf">len</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">sorted_dates</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="k">else</span> <span class="bp">None</span>
    
    <span class="c1"># Now, we run the function we defined above for the class date that we’re on
</span>    <span class="nf">create_markdown_file</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">date_str</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">content</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">previous_class</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">next_class</span><span class="p">)</span> 
    
    <span class="c1"># For the next iteration, we set the date from the current iteration to the 
</span>    <span class="c1"># previous_class date for the next iteration... pretty nice, huh?
</span>    <span class="n">previous_class</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">date_str</span> 
</code></pre></div></div> <p>Add this all together, et voilà. You have a list of classes for your entire semester of election law. Not only that, but you have the readings and topic pre-loaded, though you mileage may vary since some professors will sometimes make changes to these parts of the class as the semester progresses. Additionally, the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">next_class</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">previous_class</code> elements will show up in the frontmatter of your notes and allow you to cycle through class date sequentially, which can be a substantial quality-of-life improvement.</p> <p>If you want to back up your application, I recommend using a Git repository, and suggest using Github specifically to host your notes. Other commentators can provide better instructions than I can on how to implement this, but I’ll note that there are Obsidian plugins that help facilitate automatic synchronization of your local Obsidian vault with the remote repository that you’ve backed it up to. If you’re using the iOS app, I recommend using Working Copy. The pro version of Working Copy is free for students who are part of the Github developer program, at least as of March, 2025, and it comes with some useful Shortcuts for you to automate synchronization just like you can do with the desktop application.<d-footnote>See eg. Ginter (2019)</d-footnote></p> <h4 id="e-conclusions-etc">e. conclusions, etc</h4> <p>I won’t expound too greatly on the great successes that Jade finds after law school, no doubt a direct result of her excellent and well-considered method for managing knowledge. I will, however, take a little bit of space to reflect on how she has positioned herself. Notes are not useful unless they can be understood within the contexts they were intended to serve. What I mean is that a note written for your future self is not useful unless it’s configured so that your future self can understand it; likewise, for notes written to accomplish short-run goals. A dusting of organization using high level folders, a standard naming convention, and even a set of common subheaders for certain categories of notes (eg. always having Facts, Question, Holding, and Analysis headers for notes corresponding to legal cases) can keep things predictable and reduce the complexity of your notes and the time it takes to manage them, and allow you to accomplish both short- and long-run intellectual goals. This way of structuring notes today can position Jade to earn excellent grades and, later, to succeed in a top law firm or competitive judicial clerkship where she needs to be able to wrap her head around a wide range of complicated topics on tight timeframes. Likewise, other future-oriented practices, like using an <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">#idea</code> tag to designate novel ideas as you take notes, can situate you to exploit intellectual opportunities later in life, when time and expertise might permit the writing of an academic journal article or to take some other action on a topic of interest from your school days. So, if you’ve read this far, I earnestly hope - all the more so if you are one of my students - that you take this as an opportunity to think about what your goals are in writing notes and, if you feel like now is a good time to reconsider the systems you build around those goals, that you use this essay as a resource to do so.</p> <div style="display: none;"> <d-cite key="ahrens2017smartnotes"></d-cite> <d-cite key="carnegie2007educating"></d-cite> <d-cite key="forte2022building"></d-cite> <d-cite key="georgetown2020legalacademy"></d-cite> <d-cite key="ginter2019ulysses"></d-cite> <d-cite key="hollis-brusky2019ideas"></d-cite> <d-cite key="seifter2022unwritten"></d-cite> <d-cite key="spolsky2018gamification"></d-cite> <d-cite key="sweigart2020automate"></d-cite> <d-cite key="teles2010rise"></d-cite> <d-cite key="vik2020zettelkasten"></d-cite> </div>]]></content><author><name>Sig Janoska-Bedi</name></author><category term="essays"/><category term="pedagogy"/><category term="code"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[and why you should care]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">modeling a horse race</title><link href="https://signebedi.github.io/blog/2023/liberalism-conservatism/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="modeling a horse race"/><published>2023-10-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-10-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://signebedi.github.io/blog/2023/liberalism-conservatism</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://signebedi.github.io/blog/2023/liberalism-conservatism/"><![CDATA[<p>I have the distinct pleasure of teaching a course this semester on how liberalism and conservatism shaped American history. Part of the difficulty of teaching this subject is in helping students understand how and why the underlying concepts change over time. This presents an interesting “teaching methods” challenge that I’ve contemplated throughout the semester and struggled to find a good solution for.</p> <p>I view this fundamentally as a definitional problem: it’s hard to pin down a comprehensive meaning for liberalism or conservatism, partly because of the long, complex history of the two traditions, partly because of the mixing of theories that practical politics tends to effectuate. These are ideas in motion. Neither set of ideas fit neatly into categories - each constitutes a theory of government, to be sure, but also a framework for applied policymaking, a literary and epistemic tradition, and an ideology for democratic politics. Early in the class, we tackled this by building mind maps of both concepts, establishing links and anti-links to gain a better understanding of each theory’s tenets and how they related to each other. Recurring themes for liberalism tended to include concepts like change, progress, economic freedom, liberty, and equality, while conservatism usually included tradition, religion, hierarchy, and stability. But this still didn’t account for changes to the ideas over time - that is, why a tenet like “tradition” might look different if you examine how the principle is carried out in the 18th Century as opposed to the 21st Century.</p> <p>One possible approach I considered was a participatory model where we created actual hats labeled “conservative” and “liberal” that students could wear as part of the classroom activities to think through historical problems from different perspectives, which would, at least in theory, free them from needing to take personal responsibility for challenging world views while allowing us still to derive learning value from these, and which we could introduce more complex sub-variants to as the course progressed (an “economic liberal” hat, for example). I decided against using this as my initial approach, however, because I felt it put too much pressure on students early in the semester - though it may prove a useful activity later on when students are more comfortable with the subject matter.</p> <p>Another approach, however, would be using heuristics to simplify complex ideas. In law school, I took Trusts and Estates with a remarkable and engaging professor named Howard Erlanger, and part of his teaching method involved approaching complex ideas through a set of “Erlanger’s Paradoxes” - a sort of theoretical shorthand to help students reach analytical conclusions faster given a limited set of facts. These were especially useful when the law neither said what it meant, or meant what it said. “If you don’t know if you have marital property [in Wisconsin],” his first principle stated, “then you do.” I had a chance to sit down with him and pick his brain about my somewhat comparable pedagogical predicament, leading to what I’ve taken to calling, in conscious emulation of my intellectual upstream, “Sig’s Abstractions.”</p> <p>I’m writing this post <em>in media res</em> (with mixed feelings about my students reading it) because doing so has been helpful in developing these abstractions further, as well as a language to discuss them with my students. It’s important to note, however - and I hope my students understand this - that these are only a shorthand primarily rooted in the American context, and the interpretations of liberalism and conservatism presented here may grate with other academic, especially non-American perspectives on the same.</p> <h4 id="i-the-horse-race">I. The Horse Race</h4> <p>The first problem I’ve experienced in teaching liberalism and conservatism is, put simply, why neither of these ideas look exactly the same as they did in the past. As an example: Adam Smith’s liberalism placed, I think, a far greater emphasis on free markets than today’s liberalism, which has adopted intervention as a core tenet. To square this circle, we would probably need to reach two conclusions: first, that liberalism outpaces conservatism; second, that conservatism is nonetheless also a “moving” idea that changes over time, though probably not at the same pace as liberalism. I find that this is best illustrated by the analogy of a horse race: if liberalism and conservatism were two horses that, for the purpose of the discussion, are situated at the same starting gate, then which horse will outpace the other at any arbitrary time?</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-10-22-horse_race-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-10-22-horse_race-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-10-22-horse_race-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/2023-10-22-horse_race.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Illustration of the horse race (source: author) </div> <p>If you put your money on liberalism, then you’ve correctly made sense of the analogy. But, a more challenging question: does the fact that liberalism outpaces conservatism mean that the conservatism horse never left the starting post? Of course not. Conservatism generally tries to keep pace with the faster horse, but never passes it because, to convervatives, the race is not necessarily to the fastest. Perhaps, to take this analogy a bit further, conservatism wishes that the race were oriented in the opposite direction, but at the same time doesn’t want to be left too far behind by the faster horse running the other way. Thus, we see conservatism today adopt all manner of ideas that, in the 19th Century, might have seemed alien to those who identified with that label.</p> <h4 id="ii-the-caduceus">II. The Caduceus</h4> <p>The second teaching problem I’ve experienced is why the two ideas seem sometimes to leverage similar language and ideas, or might be used to justify the same policies, despite differing significantly in their intellectual tradition and worldview. A good way to think about this might be that liberalism and conservatism are not ideas that exist in a vacuum - their scholars read each other’s work and respond to the same events, and intertexts are inevitable when given enough time. A useful way to visualize how concepts might converge is the image of the caduceus, a symbol that depicts two snakes wrapped around a staff and conveys a sense of mediation and diplomacy. Beyond my personal predilection for the classics, I’ve found that students are also interested in the strange symbols from antiquity and think that the novelty of the image helps grab and keep their attention.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0" style="height: 50%;"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-10-22-caduceus-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-10-22-caduceus-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-10-22-caduceus-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/2023-10-22-caduceus.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Two serpents wrapped around a staff (source: Ernest de Sarzec - Choquin de Sarzec, Ernest (1832-1901), Public domain, via Wikimedia Commons) </div> <p>So, in visualizing this idea in a manner similar to the first, we might plot liberalism and conservatism as a wave function and its inverse, with the two waves periodically intersecting with one another.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-10-22-intertwined_lines-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-10-22-intertwined_lines-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-10-22-intertwined_lines-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/2023-10-22-intertwined_lines.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Illustration of two intersecting waves (source: author) </div> <h4 id="iii-wedges">III. Wedges</h4> <p>The complexities of liberalism and conservatism often produce, not just distinctions between these theories, but also the divergences within each. This phenomenon, which I will here call “wedges,” refers to the internal splits that can occur within a single theoretical framework. This concept stands in contrast to the “caduceus” model described above, where similar language and outcomes emerge from different frameworks. Here, we observe how a single framework can yield different substantive results.</p> <p>I’ve taken to referring to this phenomenon as liminal divergence, or sometimes issue-based dichotomization if we’d like the emphasize the result instead of the <em>modus</em>, by which I mean cases where individuals or groups that adhere to conservative or liberal principles hold different, often-contradictory positions on substantive policy issues when compared to others that adhere to the same principles. Can a liberal thinker authentically justify (as opposed to cynically, or for political purposes) qualified immunity based on a liberal worldview? Can a conservative thinker justify affirmative action based on a conservative worldview?</p> <p>These dichotomies, I would argue, don’t emerge solely from the differences between opposing worldviews but rather emerge from the varying emphases on and interpretations of liminal concepts and controversies by individuals who subscribe to the same general political philosophy when they confront real events and issues relevant to their own lives. Here, I use the term “liminal concept” or controversy to describe the fundamental, often contentious ideas that exist at the boundaries or thresholds of a single political philosophy. They might be matters of interpretation, where different scholars approach, accept, or reject them in different ways. They seldom make up the core tenets of that philosophy and, as a result, are left sometimes without solid treatment by the academic community and perhaps willfully ignored by political practitioners. They are neither fully embraced nor entirely rejected by any single ideological group, but instead exist in a state of ambiguity or ambivalence.</p> <p>What I mean is that it’s not clear that humans are principled creatures <em>per se</em>, even if we often try to appear so. More often, we tend to “window shop” for the principles and procedures that get us what we want.<d-footnote>There is a lot of interesting literature on this. See eg. Tiebout (1956) for discussion on decisions on where to live, Briffault (2018) 2025-7 for unprincipled behavior as it relates to federalism.</d-footnote> But I would venture that, while the variation in positioning on substantive issues is useful in understanding this behavior, such analyses would likely result in the conclusion that the behavior is “unprincipled”. However, a greater emphasis on the individual’s reaction to liminal controversies can help make sense of these behaviors as still ‘principled.’</p> <p>But what are these liminal controversies? I think there are probably too many to provide an exhaustive list here, but a few might include disagreements over the individual vs. collective, material vs. ideological, outsiders vs. a political establishment, reforming institutions vs. all-out revolution.<d-footnote>I'm sure, if this essay were longer, we could have a useful discussion of this as it relates to the Horseshoe Theory of political ideology, but this will need to be saved for another time.</d-footnote></p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-10-22-diverging_lines-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-10-22-diverging_lines-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-10-22-diverging_lines-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/2023-10-22-diverging_lines.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Illustration of issue-based divergence (source: author) </div> <h4 id="iv-the-ouroboros">IV. The Ouroboros</h4> <p>The previous conceptualizations presume that knowledge, culture, and institutions are constantly moving forward. However, this linear progression doesn’t always hold true in the real world. Ideas don’t just move forward; they also circle back, revisiting and reinterpreting past concepts. This leads us to a third teaching problem: why the ideas often seem to hearken back or revert to past approaches. Admittedly, this phenomenon is something that will become more apparent in discussions of more recent events as we are able to observe how history sometimes “repeats itself.” For example, debates around the First National Bank were largely focused on constitutional interpretation, but later debates were able to leverage experience and history as evidence for or against the bank’s rechartering.</p> <p>The practice of “hearkening back” might be a less surprising phenomenon for conservatism, which places far greater an emphasis on history and tradition - but even liberalism has a tendency toward archaics. Take, for instance, the resurgence of classical liberal ideas among libertarians. While classical liberalism emphasizes individual liberty and limited government, it’s been reinterpreted and adapted by modern libertarians to address contemporary issues. Whether or not libertarians constitute a Liberal or Conservative group will necessarily invite debate, but what’s clear is that their core tenets draw heavily from early Liberal thought.</p> <p>I think this idea is nicely modeled by the tail eater (Attic: ὁ οὐροβόρος), another ancient symbol of life, death, and rebirth - or, in a more abstract sense, the cyclicality that permeates all areas of life, to help illustrate how liberalism and conservatism don’t just move forward, but can sometimes hearken to old arrangements.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-10-22-ouroboros-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-10-22-ouroboros-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-10-22-ouroboros-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/2023-10-22-ouroboros.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> The serpent devours its own tail (source: <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Serpiente_alquimica.jpg">anonymous medieval illuminator; uploader Carlos adanero</a>, Public domain, via Wikimedia Commons) </div> <p>Represented in the same manner as the earlier concepts, it might look like two circles converging back upon themselves.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-10-22-circular_lines-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-10-22-circular_lines-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-10-22-circular_lines-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/2023-10-22-circular_lines.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Illustration of two curves converging back on themselves (source: author) </div> <p>In any event, these musings constitute a slightly cleaned up set of working notes that have evolved over the first few weeks of the academic term. Thank you for reading, and hopefully the effort has been rewarding and enjoyable.</p> <div style="display: none;"> <d-cite key="oakeshott1991"></d-cite> <d-cite key="fukuyama1992end"></d-cite> <d-cite key="tiebout1956"></d-cite> <d-cite key="briffault2018"></d-cite> </div>]]></content><author><name>Sig Janoska-Bedi</name></author><category term="essays"/><category term="pedagogy"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[abstract approaches to liberalism and conservatism]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">a brief ‘hello world’</title><link href="https://signebedi.github.io/blog/2023/hello-world/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="a brief ‘hello world’"/><published>2023-07-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-07-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://signebedi.github.io/blog/2023/hello-world</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://signebedi.github.io/blog/2023/hello-world/"><![CDATA[<p>A few weeks ago, I was very grateful to find myself backpacking on the <a href="https://superiorhiking.org/trail-section/silver-bay-to-caribou-river-wayside/">Superior Hiking Trail</a> and had the chance to relax with my group at a campground off the Beaver River, in an area north of Two Harbors, MN. I spent some time submerged in the water and attuning myself to the tranquil sounds of birdsong, the rustling of leaves in the wind, and the water lapping against nearby stones. In the overwhelming synchronicity of the moment, a few thoughts crossed my mind that I hope you’ll permit me to share here.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-07-25-beaver-creek-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-07-25-beaver-creek-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-07-25-beaver-creek-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/2023-07-25-beaver-creek.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Beaver River (source: author) </div> <h4 id="i-objects">I. Objects</h4> <p>I am incredibly grateful for the opportunities my life has provided to participate in the activities, rituals, and institutions of modern western society but, as the scope of one’s participation in these increases, so too do the transaction costs, which waste our time, frustrate us, and deprive us of perspective. We all experience these transaction costs, or at least are aware of their existence - commuting time, monthly fees, paperwork, and a thousand login credentials to websites we haven’t visited in years. On the one hand, these frustrations can be written off as the price we pay to enjoy society’s abstractions; on the other, they make life less fulfilling and breed resentment against the very things that have improved our material quality of life so much over the last century.</p> <p>What strikes me most about modernity is our remarkable preoccupation with objects. There’s a platitude we could interject here about how we have far too many “things” that sap our attention and disrupt our ability to be pleased with what we have. That’s not to say that past societies were unconcerned with material culture - they were. But my use of “object” is not perfectly synonymous with materialism, as it is strictly and directly applicable to tangible objects. Instead, my use of this term privileges a perceived shift in mindset that has occurred: from experiences, observations, and tradition toward what Michael Oakeshott might have derided as an arrogant focus on objectivity and rationalism. <d-footnote>Oakeshott (1991). 7-13.</d-footnote> I suppose my argument, if there is one, would be that this societal shift has corresponded with a shift where the “things” we have become a proxy for less tangible forms of meaning-making. I’d like to also be very clear that my argument is not intended to resemble Fukuyama’s “last man” who, with nothing meaningful left to think or do, consigns himself to a life of boredom, hedonism, and directionless toil. <d-footnote>Fukuyama (1992). xxii-xxiii.</d-footnote> Indeed, there are many problems yet to solve, and much still to give our lives some meaning. My claim, put simply, is that something about modernity has increased the scale of consumption and that, as a result, the “object” is the most available locus through which to experience the world.</p> <p>Perhaps the thing about objects, both material and otherwise, is that they can be broken, discarded, and replaced. Indeed, it has always fascinated me that a nontrivial body of evidence of ancient material culture comes from landfills. <d-footnote>Eg. Ezban (2012)</d-footnote> A fundamental principle of academia as an institution is that scholars respond to, build upon, and disprove each other’s work. This fact may help with the challenge of defining an object within the scope of this essay: the difference between an object within my usage, and the broader class of material culture, is that an object, insofar as we are talking about a discernible thing, ought to be understood as being disposable. So, I suppose there is a subjective component to this definition that asks: what is disposable to you? One person, may map significant meaning onto something’s existence, its function, or perhaps their mere possession of it; for another, that same thing may be a simple tool to throw away when its job is complete. For one, the “thing” is important in its own right, but for the other it is a mere instrumentality. So, we can probably summarize the preceding discussion as “our use of things we are willing to throw away has increased.”</p> <p>In its ephemerality, an object resembles the baited breath of the human life that, faced with urgency, must hasten to achieve its objective. Every object we grasp - and, all the more so, their accumulation <em>en masse</em> - is a sort of Faustian Bargain, a lease on the opportunity to employ «object as tool» to attain our increasingly lofty goals within a still-very-limited lifespan. In some ways, objects invite further abstraction and social complexity. Take, for example, the vessel - an object that carries other objects, to be sure, but also - especially in Bronze Age cultures - to carry things ritual significance, like human remains. <d-footnote>See generally Cole (1979).</d-footnote> In some ways, modern life is less urgent, and objects are more readily available. But in another sense, life is far more scarce, as we are greedy for achievement or, perhaps, society is greedy to harvest individual achievements to its own ends. To twist an old tale: we construct ever-waxier wings in an effort to strive closer and closer to the sun.</p> <p>For some reason, this makes me think of C.G. Jung’s writings on typology - especially what he referred to as the extroverted thinking type. On this, Jung stated that “the extroverted thinking type will, by definition, be a man whose constant endeavor…. is to make all his activities dependent on intellectual conclusions, which in the last resort are always oriented by objective data, whether these be external facts or generally accepted ideas.” <d-footnote>Jung (1921). ¶ 585.</d-footnote> Modernity is shaped in a manner favoring this kind of thinking, and it rewards extroverted thinkers with plenty of objects, real and figurative, through which to engage with the world.</p> <p>At the same time, the structure of our society seems to have deprived those who do not think in this way of proportionately meaningful symbols through which to engage with themselves and others. Here, the introverted types - especially the intuitive and feeling types - are useful to bring into the conversation because this category describes those to whom subjective images provide much more meaning, and to whom the strictures of every day social life might sometimes seem, at best, superfluous and, at worst, grating.<d-footnote>Eg. Ibid. ¶ 638, 642. On this, Jung writes that "introverted feeling is conditioned subjectively and is only secondarily concerned with the object," while primarily concerning itself with "deeply felt, unconscious images."</d-footnote> There is further analogy to be made on the relationship between social order, decadence, and nature - but this probably warrants a separate discussion <d-footnote>My knowledge on this subject is limited, but Paglia (1990) presents an interesting, if maybe controversial, way of thinking about the world in terms of Apollonian order and Dionysian nature. There is also Nietzsche...</d-footnote></p> <h4 id="ii-masks">II. Masks</h4> <p>One hypothesis I have is that our preoccupation with objects means that we will more often tend to “mask” when we participate in social institutions, insofar as engaging with the world outside of ourselves - full of things and people with their own interests, ideologies, and agency - requires us to sacrifice certain aspects of our true self in order to facilitate a functioning society. I am not trying to assert that masks are bad <em>per se</em>, but instead point out some of their drawbacks. To one person, masking might induce a stress response when the mask deprives them of opportunities for genuine self-expression; to another, masks might be a comfortable way to avoid outside scrutiny or introspection, which, though sometimes difficult, is nonetheless good for long term satisfaction in life. Nor am I trying to assert that masks are some kind of new phenomenon, but rather that modernity has given them new forms and thrusts them upon us at every turn: literal mask wearing, like Comic-Con attendees dressing as their favorite heroes and villains; physical masks, like a face-lift or nose job; abstract masks, like a professionally-curated social media presence - all of these have given us new pathways to hide ourselves away from each other, and ultimately, I would argue, from ourselves.</p> <p>Widespread masking threatens the usefulness of an individual’s social experiences, observations, and perceptions, because we employ our senses to make sense of the world and seek after truth. Masks evince a comparable effect to the shadows in Plato’s Allegory of the Cave. But I think that we also understand the disadvantages of an “over masked” society and have developed approaches for recognizing and moving away from a masked persona when doing so promotes the social good. I think a good example is the image of the third eye, itself a sort of mask that is commonly used in art to represent introspection and self-awareness, helping us understand and realize certain truths about ourselves. <d-footnote>Eg. Napier (1987). 139, 149.</d-footnote> It is commonly worn in subcontinental culture as a tilaka, which is a sort of mask drawn on a person’s forehead.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-07-25-tika-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-07-25-tika-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-07-25-tika-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/2023-07-25-tika.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Nepali sadhu with a tilaka on his forehead (Source: <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Kathmandu,_Nepal,_Sadhu.jpg">© Vyacheslav Argenberg / http://www.vascoplanet.com/</a>, <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">CC BY 4.0</a>, via Wikimedia Commons) </div> <p>The third eye gazes inward, yes. But it is also an instrument of destruction. In the Hindu tradition, Shiva’s third eye opens to eradicate evil from the universe. Likewise, the third eye as a human symbol might propose to uproot those things about ourselves that are not desirable and force us instead to reckon with the subjective self whether we want to or not. Thus, it is sort of an “anti-mask”, as we train it inward just as we might display it outward; we employ it as a way of realization, rather than as a form of obfuscation. My favorite illustration of the third eye serving this function is Frank Herbert’s Dune, where characters invoke the image to overcome paroxysms of fear.<d-footnote>Herbert (1965).</d-footnote></p> <div class="poem"> <div class="stanza"> <div class="line"> <div class="original"></div> <div class="translation">I must not fear. Fear is the mind-killer.</div> </div> <div class="line"> <div class="original"></div> <div class="translation">Fear is the little-death that brings total obliteration.</div> </div> <div class="line"> <div class="original"></div> <div class="translation">I will face my fear.</div> </div> <div class="line"> <div class="original"></div> <div class="translation">I will permit it to pass over me and through me.</div> </div> <div class="line"> <div class="original"></div> <div class="translation">And when it has gone past <strong>I will turn the inner eye to see its path</strong>.</div> </div> <div class="line"> <div class="original"></div> <div class="translation">Where the fear has gone there will be nothing.</div> </div> <div class="line"> <div class="original"></div> <div class="translation">Only I will remain.</div> </div> </div> </div> <h4 id="iii-flow">III. Flow</h4> <p>Introspection in general can be a troubling business because it forces us to confront certain aspects of ourselves about which we are least comfortable and have hidden away from the gaze of others. But to build a life that is fulfilling, we must sometimes endure discomfort. Some people reject, rebel, or run away from themselves (through, for example, drug use or vapid consumerism) or from society (like a hermit who goes to live in the woods). But there may be a third option in the cultivation of flow, by which I mean the feeling of wellness and satisfaction that we experience through total, active involvement of the self with the world around it. <d-footnote>Csikszentmihalyi (1997). 71.</d-footnote> Flow is interesting to me because it is something that allows us to immerse ourselves in society’s activities without alienating us from the self. The chief accomplishment of someone who reaches flow quite often, according to Mihaly Csikszentmihalyi, is the “Autotelic Personality,” which refers to one who enjoys their activities for their own sake, rather than for the material benefits they might bestow.</p> <p>Take, for example, my decision to start this blog. In many ways, doing so is antithetical to my <a href="https://www.urbandictionary.com/define.php?term=Midwest%20Nice">midwest-nice</a> outlook toward life, which entails, amongst other things, an appreciation of humility in myself and others. Something about writing about myself or, even worse, presuming others might want to read what I write strikes me as particularly self-indulgent and inconsistent with my worldview. And yet, here I am, and here you are. At the risk sounding somewhat attenuated, there’s an essay called “This is Water” by David Foster Wallace - well rehearsed across American college campuses at this point, but nonetheless useful to us here - where he tells the story of a religious man and an atheist arguing over the existence of God. The atheist shares a story about how he had been caught in a snowstorm a few weeks before and prayed to God to save him. The religious man is relieved because, seeing as the atheist survived, it was clear to him that it was God who had saved him. But the atheist writes him off, instead dedicating his salvation to a few passers-by who pulled him from the snow.<d-footnote>Wallace (2009).</d-footnote> Wallace highlights how both men mapped their subjective beliefs onto the atheist’s life-or-death experience, without necessarily directing their attention toward, or cultivating any manner of consciousness about, the other’s perspective. Wallace thought of this as being a problem of compassion, but I think it is a problem of attention. Preventing situations like these is exactly the social function that experiences like flow can serve. By paying closer attention, we can, at the very least, come to understand the worldviews of others instead of being locked behind the limiting bars of our own.</p> <h4 id="iv-interfaces">IV. Interfaces</h4> <p>I am somebody who primarily views the world through the lens of interfaces. Facilitating interconnectivity between things that are understood to be different-in-kind is a deeply pleasing process that is, to me, its own reward. The concept of an interface is something we typically apply to man-made systems, instruments, and ideas; but this concept is useful in other areas of life. What I appreciated about the moment I spent in the Beaver River was the sparks of interconnectivity I felt between myself and the world around me, and it was my attention to the world around me that fastened me to it in that moment. Throughout my life, I have often drunk when I was thirsty and clothed myself when I was cold but, in the theme of Wallace’s essay, this was a rare moment where I could recognize that it was indeed water that I was swimming in. I sat in the Beaver River for awhile before, standing up, I felt a warm breeze wrap itself around my body, recalling a verse from high school English. <d-footnote>Chaucer (c. 1400). 1.1.</d-footnote></p> <div class="poem"> <div class="stanza"> <div class="line"> <div class="original">Whan Zephirus eek with his sweete breeth</div> <div class="translation">When the West Wind also with its sweet breath</div> </div> <div class="line"> <div class="original">Inspired hath in every holt and heeth</div> <div class="translation">In every wood and field has breathed life into</div> </div> <div class="line"> <div class="original">The tendre croppes, and the yonge sonne</div> <div class="translation">The tender new leaves, and the young sun</div> </div> <div class="line"> <div class="original">Hath in the Ram his half cours yronne,</div> <div class="translation">Has run half its course in Aries</div> </div> </div> </div> <p>So, I’ve decided to call this blog <a href="https://referenceworks.brillonline.com/entries/brill-s-new-pauly/zephyrus-e12216400"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">zephyrus</code></a>, something I am doing ‘for its own sake’ where I can lay down my masks and reflect upon &amp; celebrate the human experience through intellectual lenses available to me. I hope that, like a summer breeze, these musings may be a source of comfort to you as they are to me.</p> <div style="display: none;"> <d-cite key="oakeshott1991"></d-cite> <d-cite key="fukuyama1992end"></d-cite> <d-cite key="ezban2012trash"></d-cite> <d-cite key="coles1979bronze"></d-cite> <d-cite key="jung1921psychological"></d-cite> <d-cite key="paglia1990sexual"></d-cite> <d-cite key="napier1987masks"></d-cite> <d-cite key="csikszentmihalyi1997finding"></d-cite> <d-cite key="herbert1965dune"></d-cite> <d-cite key="chaucer1400"></d-cite> <d-cite key="wallace2009"></d-cite> </div>]]></content><author><name>Sig Janoska-Bedi</name></author><category term="essays"/><category term="meta"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[let's get this party started]]></summary></entry></feed>