<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://signebedi.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://signebedi.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2023-10-22T14:19:18+00:00</updated><id>https://signebedi.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Software Engineer. Classicist. Social Scientist. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">modeling a horse race</title><link href="https://signebedi.github.io/blog/2023/liberalism-conservatism/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="modeling a horse race"/><published>2023-10-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-10-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://signebedi.github.io/blog/2023/liberalism-conservatism</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://signebedi.github.io/blog/2023/liberalism-conservatism/"><![CDATA[<p>I have the distinct pleasure of teaching a course this semester on how Liberalism and Conservatism shaped American history. Part of the difficulty of teaching this subject is in helping students understand how and why the underlying concepts change over time. This presents an interesting “teaching methods” challenged that I’ve contemplated throughout the semester and struggled to find a good solution for.</p> <p>Fundamentally, I view this as a definitional problem: it’s hard to pin down a comprehensive meaning for Liberalism or Conservatism. Early in the class, we tackled this by building mind maps of both ideas, establishing links and anti-links to gain a better understanding. Recurring themes for Liberalism tended to include concepts like change, liberty, and equality, while Conservatism usually included tradition, hierarchy, and stability. But this still didn’t account for changes to the ideas over time - that is, why “tradition, hierarchy, and stability” might look different if you examine how these principles are carried out in the 18th Century as opposed to the 21st Century.</p> <p>In law school, I took my class on Trusts and Estates with a remarkable and engaging professor named Howard Erlanger, and part of his teaching method involved approaching complex ideas through a set of “Erlanger Paradoxes”. I had a chance to sit down with him and pick his brain about my somewhat comparable pedagogical predicament, leading to what I’ve taken to calling, in conscious emulation of my intellectual upstream, “Sig’s Abstractions.”</p> <p>I’m writing this post <em>in media res</em> (and hoping that my students don’t read it) because doing so has been helpful in developing the abstractions further and developing a language to discuss them with my discussion groups. It’s important to note, however - and I hope my students understand this - that the discussions here are primarily rooted in the American context and the interpretations of Liberalism and Conservatism presented may grate with non-American perspectives on the same.</p> <h4 id="i-the-horse-race">I. The horse race</h4> <p>The first problem I’ve experienced in teaching Liberalism and Conservatism is, put simply, why neither of these ideas look exactly the same as they did in the past. As an example: Adam Smith’s Liberalism placed, I think, a far greater emphasis on free markets than today’s Liberalism, which has adopted intervention as a core tenet. To square this circle, we need to reach two conclusions: first, that Liberalism outpaces conservatism; second, that Conservatism is nonetheless also a “moving” idea that changes over time, though perhaps not at the same pace as Liberalism. I find that this is best illustrated by the analogy of a horse race: if Liberalism and Conservatism were two horses that, for the purpose of the discussion, are situated at the same starting gate, then which horse will eventually outpace the other?</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-10-22-horse_race-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-10-22-horse_race-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-10-22-horse_race-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/2023-10-22-horse_race.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Illustration of the horse race (source: author) </div> <p>If you put your money on Liberalism, then you’ve correctly made sense of the analogy. But, a more challenging question: does the fact that Liberalism outpaces Conservatism mean that the Conservatism horse never left the starting post? Of course not. Conservatism tried to keep up with the faster horse but never outpaces it because, to it, the race is not necessarily to the fastest alone. Thus, we see Conservatism today adopt all manner of ideas that, in the 19th Century, might have seemed utterly alien to those who used that label to describe themselves.</p> <h4 id="ii-caduceus">II. Caduceus</h4> <p>The second teaching problem I’ve experienced is why the two ideas seem sometimes to leverage similar language and ideas, or might be used to justify the same policies, despite differing significantly in their intellectual tradition and worldview. A good way to think about this might be that Liberalism and Conservatism are not ideas that exist in a vacuum - their scholars read each other’s work and respond to the same events, and intertexts are inevitable when given enough time. A useful way to visualize how concepts might converge is the image of the caduceus, a symbol that depicts two snakes wrapped around a staff and aptly conveys a sense of mediation and diplomacy.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-10-22-caduceus-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-10-22-caduceus-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-10-22-caduceus-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/2023-10-22-caduceus.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Two serpents wrapped around a staff (source: Ernest de Sarzec - Choquin de Sarzec, Ernest (1832-1901), Public domain, via Wikimedia Commons) </div> <p>So, in visualizing this abstraction in a manner similar to the first, we might plot Liberalism and Conservatism as a wave function and its inverse, with the two waves intersecting with one another periodically.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-10-22-intertwined_lines-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-10-22-intertwined_lines-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-10-22-intertwined_lines-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/2023-10-22-intertwined_lines.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Illustration of two intersecting waves (source: author) </div> <h4 id="iii-ouroboros">III. Ouroboros</h4> <p>Finally, the two previous abstractions presume that knowledge, culture, and institutions are constantly moving forward. However, this linear progression doesn’t always hold true in the real world. Ideas don’t just move forward; they also circle back, revisiting and reinterpreting past concepts. This leads us to the final teaching problem: why the ideas often seem to hearken back or revert to past approaches. Admittedly, this phenomenon is something that will become more apparent in discussions of more recent events as we are able to observe how history sometimes “repeats itself.” Further, this might be a less surprising phenomenon for Conservatism, which places far greater an emphasis on history and tradition - but even Liberalism has a tendency toward archaics. Take, for instance, the resurgence of classical liberal ideas among libertarians. While classical liberalism emphasizes individual liberty and limited government, it’s been reinterpreted and adapted by modern libertarians to address contemporary issues. Whether or not libertarians constitute a Liberal or Conservative party will necessarily invite debate, but what’s clear is that their core tenets draw moe from early Liberal thought that Conservative thought.</p> <p>I think this idea is nicely modeled by the tail eater (Attic: οὐροβόρος), a symbol of life, death, and rebirth - or, in a more abstract sense, the cyclicality that permeates all areas of life, to help illustrate how Liberalism and Conservatism don’t just move forward, but can sometimes return to old arrangements.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-10-22-ouroboros-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-10-22-ouroboros-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-10-22-ouroboros-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/2023-10-22-ouroboros.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> The serpent devours its own tail (source: <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Serpiente_alquimica.jpg">anonymous medieval illuminator; uploader Carlos adanero</a>, Public domain, via Wikimedia Commons) </div> <p>Represented in the same manner as the earlier two abstractions, it might look like two circles converging back upon themselves.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-10-22-circular_lines-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-10-22-circular_lines-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-10-22-circular_lines-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/2023-10-22-circular_lines.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Illustration of the ouroboros (source: author) </div> ]]></content><author><name>Sig Janoska-Bedi</name></author><category term="essays"/><category term="meta"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[abstract approaches to Liberalism and Conservatism]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">a brief ‘hello world’</title><link href="https://signebedi.github.io/blog/2023/hello-world/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="a brief ‘hello world’"/><published>2023-07-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-07-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://signebedi.github.io/blog/2023/hello-world</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://signebedi.github.io/blog/2023/hello-world/"><![CDATA[<p>A few weeks ago, I was backpacking on the <a href="https://superiorhiking.org/trail-section/silver-bay-to-caribou-river-wayside/">Superior Hiking Trail</a> and had the chance to relax with my group at a campground off the Beaver River, in an area north of Two Harbors, MN. I spent some time sitting half-submerged in the water and zoning out to the tranquil sounds of birdsong, the rustling of leaves in the wind, and the water lapping against nearby stones as the others set up their tents. In the overwhelming synchronicity of the moment, a few thoughts crossed my mind that I’d like to share here.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-07-25-beaver-creek-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-07-25-beaver-creek-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-07-25-beaver-creek-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/2023-07-25-beaver-creek.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Beaver River (source: author) </div> <h4 id="i-objects">I. Objects</h4> <p>I am incredibly grateful for the opportunities my life has provided to participate in the activities, rituals, and institutions of modern western society but, as the scope of my participation in these has increased, so too have the transaction costs, which waste our time, frustrate us, and deprive us of perspective. We all experience these transaction costs, or at least are aware of their existence - commuting time, monthly fees, paperwork, and a thousand login credentials to websites we haven’t visited for years. On one hand, these frustrations can be written off as the price we pay to enjoy society’s abstractions; on the other, they make life less fulfilling and breed resentment against the very things that have improved our material quality of life so much over the last century.</p> <p>What strikes me most about modernity is our remarkable preoccupation with objects. That’s not to say that past societies were unconcerned with material culture - they were. But my use of “object” is not perfectly synonymous with materialis, privileging instead a shift in mindset from experiences, history, and tradition toward Oakeshott-style rationalism. <d-footnote>Oakeshott (1991). 7-13.</d-footnote> My claim is that an increased scale of consumption has made the object the most available locus through which to experience the world. In his writings on typology, C.G. Jung stated that “the extroverted thinking type will, by definition, be a man whose constant endeavor…. is to make all his activities dependent on intellectual conclusions, which in the last resort are always oriented by objective data, whether these be external facts or generally accepted ideas.” <d-footnote>Jung (1921). ¶ 585.</d-footnote> Modernity rewards the extroverted thinkers with plenty of objects, real and figurative, through which to engage with the world, and at the same time deprives their counterparts - the introverted feeling types - of proportionately meaningful symbols through which to engage with themselves. The introverted feeling type is useful to bring into the conversation because it characterizes someone for whom the subjective images of the self suffice in providing meaning, and to whom the structs of every day social life might seem, at best, superfluous; at worst, grating.<d-footnote>Ibid. ¶ 638, 642. On this, Jung writes that "introverted feeling is conditioned subjectively and is only secondarily concerned with the object," while primarily concerning itself with "deeply felt, unconscious images."</d-footnote></p> <h4 id="ii-masks">II. Masks</h4> <p>Our preoccupation with objects means that we will tend to wear masks when we participate in social institutions, insofar as engaging with the world outside of ourselves - full of things and people with their own interests, ideologies, and agency - requires us to sacrifice certain aspects of our true self in order to facilitate the function of society. I am not trying to assert that masks are bad per se, but instead point out some of their drawbacks. To one person, masks might be a source of stress when the mask deprives them of opportunities for genuine self-expression; to another person, masks might be a comfortable way to avoid introspection or personal growth, which, though sometimes difficult, is nonetheless good for long term satisfaction in life. Nor am I trying to assert that masks are some kind of new phenomenon, but rather that modernity has given them new forms and thrusts them upon us at every turn: literal mask wearing, like Comic-Con attendees dressing as their favorite heroes and villains; physical masks, like a face-lift or plastic surgery; abstract masks, like a professionally-curated social media presence - all of these have given us new pathways to hide ourselves away from each other, and from ourselves. But I think that humans understand the disadvantages of an “over masked” society and have developed structs for recognizing and moving away from a masked persona when doing so promotes the social good. I think a good example of such a struct is the image of the third eye, itself a sort of mask that is commonly used in art to represent introspection and self-awareness, helping us understand and realize certain truths about ourselves. <d-footnote>Napier (1987). 139, 149.</d-footnote> It is commonly worn in subcontinental culture as a tilaka, which is a sort of mask drawn on a person’s forehead.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-07-25-tika-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-07-25-tika-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-07-25-tika-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/2023-07-25-tika.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Nepali sadhu with a tilaka on his forehead (Source: <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Kathmandu,_Nepal,_Sadhu.jpg">© Vyacheslav Argenberg / http://www.vascoplanet.com/</a>, <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">CC BY 4.0</a>, via Wikimedia Commons) </div> <p>The third eye gazes inward, yes. But it is also an instrument of destruction. In the Hindu tradition, Shiva’s third eye opens to destroy evil from the universe. Likewise, the third eye as a human symbol proposes to uproot those things about ourselves that are not desirable and force us instead to reckon with the subjective self. In that way, it is sort of an “anti-mask”, as we train it inward just as we might display it outward; we employ it as a way of realization, rather than as a form of obfuscation. My favorite illustration of the third eye serving this function is Frank Herbert’s Dune, where characters invoke the image to overcome their fear.<d-footnote>Herbert (1965).</d-footnote></p> <div class="poem"> <div class="stanza"> <div class="line"> <div class="original"></div> <div class="translation">I must not fear. Fear is the mind-killer.</div> </div> <div class="line"> <div class="original"></div> <div class="translation">Fear is the little-death that brings total obliteration.</div> </div> <div class="line"> <div class="original"></div> <div class="translation">I will face my fear.</div> </div> <div class="line"> <div class="original"></div> <div class="translation">I will permit it to pass over me and through me.</div> </div> <div class="line"> <div class="original"></div> <div class="translation">And when it has gone past I will turn the inner eye to see its path.</div> </div> <div class="line"> <div class="original"></div> <div class="translation">Where the fear has gone there will be nothing.</div> </div> <div class="line"> <div class="original"></div> <div class="translation">Only I will remain.</div> </div> </div> </div> <h4 id="iii-flow">III. Flow</h4> <p>Introspection can be a troubling business because it forces us to confront certain aspects of ourselves about which we are least comfortable and have hidden away from the gaze of others. But to build a life that is fulfilling, we must sometimes endure discomfort. Some people reject, rebel, or run away from themselves (through, for example, drug use or vapid consumerism) or from society (like a hermit who goes to live in the woods). But there may be a third option in the cultivation of flow, by which I mean the feeling of ecstasy that we experience through total, active involvement of the self with the world around it. <d-footnote>Csikszentmihalyi (1997). 71.</d-footnote> Flow is interesting to me because it is something that allows us to immerse ourselves in society’s activities (or activities outside of society, like backpacking) without alienating us from the self. The chief accomplishment of someone who reaches flow quite often is the “Autotelic Personality,” which refers to one who enjoys their activities for their own sake, rather than for the material benefits they might bestow.</p> <p>Take, for example, my decision to start this blog. In many ways, doing so is antithetical to my <a href="https://www.urbandictionary.com/define.php?term=Midwest%20Nice">midwest-nice</a> outlook toward life, which entails, amongst other things, an appreciation of humility in myself and others. Something about writing about myself or, even worse, presuming others might want to read about me strikes me as particularly self-indulgent and inconsistent with my worldview. And yet, here I am, and here you are. At the risk sounding somewhat attenuated, there’s an essay called “This is Water” by David Foster Wallace - well rehearsed across American college campuses at this point, but nonetheless useful to us here - where he tells the story of a religious man and an atheist arguing over the existence of God. The atheist shares a story about how he had been caught in a snowstorm a few weeks before and prayed to God to save him. The religious man is convinced that it was God who saved him, while the atheist writes him off, instead dedicating his salvation to a few passers-by who pulled him from the snow.<d-footnote>Wallace (2009).</d-footnote> Wallace highlights how each man mapped his subjective beliefs onto the atheist’s life-or-death experience, without necessarily directing their attention toward, or cultivating any manner of consciousness about, the other’s perspective.</p> <h4 id="iv-interfaces">IV. Interfaces</h4> <p>I am somebody who primarily views the world through the lens of <a href="https://www.ibm.com/topics/api">interfaces</a>. Facilitating interconnectivity between systems - in the abstract sense - is a deeply pleasing process that is, to me, its own reward. I usually apply this idea to manmade systems, instruments, and ideas; but I am very grateful to have discovered that this concept is useful in other areas of life. What I appreciated about the moment I spent in the Beaver River was the sparks of interconnectivity I felt between my subjective self and the objective world around it as my attention fastened to it. Throughout my life, I have often drunk water when I was thirsty and covered myself in blankets when I was cold but, in the theme of Wallace’s essay, this was a rare moment where I could recognize the water I was swimming in. After sitting in the Beaver River for awhile, I stood up and felt a warm breeze brush against my limbs, recalling a verse I had memorized in my youth. <d-footnote>Chaucer (c. 1400). 1.1.</d-footnote></p> <div class="poem"> <div class="stanza"> <div class="line"> <div class="original">Whan Zephirus eek with his sweete breeth</div> <div class="translation">When the West Wind also with its sweet breath</div> </div> <div class="line"> <div class="original">Inspired hath in every holt and heeth</div> <div class="translation">In every wood and field has breathed life into</div> </div> <div class="line"> <div class="original">The tendre croppes, and the yonge sonne</div> <div class="translation">The tender new leaves, and the young sun</div> </div> <div class="line"> <div class="original">Hath in the Ram his half cours yronne,</div> <div class="translation">Has run half its course in Aries</div> </div> </div> </div> <p>So, I’ve decided to call this blog <a href="https://referenceworks.brillonline.com/entries/brill-s-new-pauly/zephyrus-e12216400"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">zephyrus</code></a>, something I am doing ‘for its own sake’ where I can lay down the masks compelled unto me by society and reflect upon &amp; celebrate themes of aesthetic beauty and individual uniqueness through the intellectual lenses available to me, like literature, history, computer science, law, etc. I hope that, like a summer breeze, it is a source of comfort to you as it is to me.</p> <div style="display: none;"> <d-cite key="oakeshott1991"></d-cite> <d-cite key="jung1921psychological"></d-cite> <d-cite key="napier1987masks"></d-cite> <d-cite key="csikszentmihalyi1997finding"></d-cite> <d-cite key="herbert1965dune"></d-cite> <d-cite key="chaucer1400"></d-cite> <d-cite key="wallace2009"></d-cite> </div>]]></content><author><name>Sig Janoska-Bedi</name></author><category term="essays"/><category term="meta"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[let's get this party started]]></summary></entry></feed>